Guide to the Wednesday Club Records 1920-2015 MS 3071
New-York Historical Society
Wednesday Club records
1920-2015
New-York Historical Society
Wednesday Club (New York, N.Y.)
MS 3071
1.25 Linear feet (in one record carton and one small document box)
Records of the Wednesday Club, a Manhattan-based women's group organized in 1920 to discuss current events, topics of interest, and books of the day, at Wednesday afternoon meetings held between November and May. Includes by-laws, minutes, annual reports, membership lists, programs, some correspondence, and financial accounts.
Arrangement
The Wednesday Club Records are organized in six series devised by the archivist:
Series I. By-laws and amendments, 1926-1999
Series II. Minutes, reports, membership lists, programs, etc., 1920-2015
Series III. Index cards, 1920-1949
Series IV. Correspondence, 1922-2008 (scattered)
Series V. Potential topics for discussion, 1956-1959
Series VI. Financial, 1959-1987
Historical Note
The Wednesday Club, a Manhattan-based women's group organized to discuss events, "topics of current interest and books of the day," first met on 17 November 1920 at the home of Miss Emily Sherman, 126 East 31st Street.
The Wednesday Club was born through the dissolution of the Discussion Club, a similarly-themed group formed around 1910 by women who had attended finishing classes conducted by one Mary Gass. Mrs. Gass suggested they meet regularly to learn to converse intelligently, and so appear more captivating at dinners and dances. A controversial topic of the day—the Baby Bollinger case, in which Harry J. Haiselden (1870–1919), a Chicago surgeon and eugenicist refused to perform life-saving surgery on the deformed newborn, John Bollinger (1915–1915)—led to the club's demise. In discussing the case, some members made "dreadful remarks," others giggled, so the officers decided to disband the club, citing impending war work as the reason.
In 1920, Lois Herrick, along with a few members of the original club, invited those who had given no offense at the Bollinger discussion to attend meetings of a new club to be held on alternate Wednesdays—hence the name—between November and May. Most meetings were to be led by members and given over to discussion or debate. Some dates were to feature professional speakers or discussion leaders. Meetings were to take place at members' homes, thus limiting the size of the club's roster. Sixteen members attended the first meeting to discuss "Modern Youth and Its Ways."
Topics in the ensuing 95 years of the Wednesday Club's existence have been chosen by committee from ideas submitted by the membership. At two or three meetings each year during the club's early existence, members were expected to express their views on a book they had each read. There were theater outings and site visits (e.g., the United Nations, the New York Stock Exchange). At some meetings members recited poems and read essays, or discussed hobbies and collecting interests. At others they were entertained by well-known speakers like the Algonquin Round Table wit Heywood Broun (1888–1939). Christopher Morley (1890–1957) refused their invitation by a humorous letter which must have generated discussion enough for a whole session: "My fee is One Hundred and Fifty dollars and if you say that is too much I shall be the first to agree!" (see Box 1, Folder 25).
[This note is drawn largely from "History of the Wednesday Club, 1920–1970" in Box 1, Folder 17.]
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Wednesday Club, 2015.
Scope and Contents
The Wednesday Club Records document the group's 95-year history, from its founding in 1920, through 2015, when the collection came to the New-York Historical Society. Included are printed by-laws, with amendments, issued between 1926 and 1999; minutes of committee meetings, regular meetings, and annual meetings (which typically took place in May, at the close of the club's November-May season); annual reports of the club's president; membership lists; programs for most seasons (generally in the form of lists of topics discussed); and some correspondence, chiefly regarding membership matters (e.g., letters of resignation or nominations of prospective members), but including a few letters from well-known writers invited to speak before the club (e.g., Christopher Morley). The collection includes scattered financial accounts for the period 1959–1987.
Annual reports.; Correspondence.; Ledgers (account books); Membership lists.; Minutes (administrative records); Forums (Discussion and debate); Societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Broun, Heywood, 1888-1939; Morley, Christopher, 1890-1957; Repplier, Agnes, 1855-1950; Wednesday Club (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I. By-laws and amendments, 1926-1999
  Scope and Contents
  Contains the Wednesday Club's by-laws as published in 1926, with subsequent printed and typescript amendments through 1999.
  - By-laws, 1926/36, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - By-laws, 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - By-laws, 1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - By-laws, 1950-1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - By-laws, 1976-1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II. Minutes, reports, membership lists, programs, etc., 1920-2015
  From its start in 1920, through 1933, the activities of the Wednesday Club were recorded in small notebooks which gathered minutes of meetings (regular meetings, committee meetings, and annual meetings), financial reports, membership lists, and program dates and topics. The same records were kept for later years, but they were recorded on loose sheets stored in binders or folders. The collection lacks records covering Seasons 1983/84 through 1989/90, and Seasons 1991/92 through 1996/97.
  - Season 1920/21 [volume marked "not official"], 1920-1921 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Season 1920/21 Season 1921/22, 1920-1922 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Season 1922/23 Season 1923/24 Season 1924/25 Season 1925/26 Season 1926/27 Season 1927/28, 1922-1928 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Season 1928/29 Season 1929/30 Season 1930/31 Season 1931/32 Season 1932/33, 1928-1933 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Season 1930/31 [loose items], 1930-1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Season 1933/34 Season 1934/35 Season 1935/36 Season 1936/37 Season 1938/39 Season 1939/40, 1933-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Season 1940/41 Season 1941/42 Season 1942/43 Season 1943/44 Season 1944/45 Season 1945/46 Season 1946/47 Season 1947/48 Season 1948/49 Season 1949/50 Season 1950/51 Season 1951/52, 1940-1952 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Season 1952/53, 1952-1953 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes several "Interesting compositions written by members on special summer events and trips that they took."
  - Season 1953/54 Season 1954/55 Season 1955/56 Season 1956/57 Season 1957/58 Season 1958/59 Season 1959/60, 1953-1960 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Season 1960/61 Season 1961/62 Season 1962/63 Season 1963/64 Season 1964/65, 1960-1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Season 1965/66 Season 1966/67 Season 1967/68 Season 1968/69, 1965-1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Season 1969/70, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    Contains multiple copies of a typescript "History of the Wednesday Club, 1920-1970," compiled by Gertrude Hoyt and Barbara Cheney for the club's 50th anniversary.
  - Season 1970/71 Season 1971/72 Season 1972/73 Season 1973/74 Season 1974/75 Season 1975/76 Season 1976/77 Season 1977/78 Season 1978/79 Season 1979/80 Season 1980/81 Season 1981/82 Season 1982/83, 1970-1983 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Season 1990/91, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Season 1997/98 Season 1998/99 Season 1999/2000, 1997-2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Season 2000/01 Season 2001/02 Season 2002/03 Season 2003/04 Season 2004/05 Season 2005/06 Season 2006/07 Season 2007/08 Season 2008/09 Season 2009/10, 2000-2010 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Season 2010/11 Season 2011/12 Season 2012/13 Season 2013/14 Season 2014/15, 2010-2015 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
- Series III. Index cards, 1920-1949
  Two small metal boxes holding 3x5 index cards onto which are transcribed reports, membership lists, committee members, and other data culled from the records in Series II.
  - Committees | Executive, 1930-1940 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-B)
  - Committees | Executive, 1940-1946 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-B)
  - Committees | Nominating, 1922-1929 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-A)
  - Committees | Nominating, 1930-1949 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-B)
  - Meetings and programs, 1922-1929 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-A)
  - Meetings and programs, 1930-1940 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-B)
  - Meetings and programs, 1940-1949 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-B)
  - Membership | original members, 1920-1921 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-A)
  - Membership | active members, 1922-1929 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-A)
  - Membership | some members, 1930s-1940s (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-B)
  - Membership | guest cards, 1923-1929 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-A)
  - Membership | guest cards, 1930-1949 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-B)
  - Membership | invited to join, refused, 1920s (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-A)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1920s-1949 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2-B)
- Series IV. Correspondence, 1922-2008 (scattered)
  Aside from the letters by three well-known writers (see Folders 23-25), the other correspondence in Series IV deals with club matters, e.g. letters of resignation, charitable donations in honor of deceased members, and cards of thanks.
  - Letters from Heywood Broun, 1922 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
    Contains three letters from journalist and Algonquin Round Table wit Heywood Broun (1888-1939) regarding his lecture to the Wednesday Club on 1 March 1922.
  - Letters from Agnes Repplier, 1923 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
    Contains three letters from essayist Agnes Repplier (1855-1950) regarding her upcoming lecture to the Wednesday Club, "The Failure of Success," on 16 January 1924. In the last letter, Repplier jokes that she will send a line the day before the lecture to let the club's president know she had not died in the interval.
  - Letter from Christopher Morley, [1924-1952] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
    Contains an undated letter inscribed "November 16," from writer Christopher Morley (1890-1957), on stationery for the Saturday Review of Literature, listing Morley as contributing editor. The journal began publication in 1924, and had its title shortened to Saturday Review in 1952, so Morley's humorous letter probably dates from that 28-year period. It reads, in full:
    Dear Mrs. Moffat -- Thankyou for your friendly invitation. I'm afraid I couldn't manage January 6th, as I rather expect to be out of town at that time. Possibly, if your club really wants me, we could arrange some afternoon later in that month; but I must frankly say that my terms are rather steep. There are many very friendly invitations of this sort, and one has, in self-defence, to put them on a rather brutal basis. My fee is One Hundred and Fifty dollars and if you say that is too much I shall be the first to agree! Cordially yours, Christopher Morley
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1954-1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1964-2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
  - Undated letters and notes (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
- Series V. Potential topics for discussion, 1956-1959
  This series gathers material that was kept for its discussion potential. Folder 31 includes a number of cards on which members submitted their topic ideas, such as "Do men make history, or does history (events) make men?" and "Would you prefer that our government spend less on the space program and more to ease the plight of the cities?" Similar member suggestions may also be found scattered throughout Series II.
  - Newsletters, 1956-1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29)
    Includes twelve issues of Vital Issues: "A Discussion Guide for Better Informed Americans" (1956-1957); "Twenty Questions on Civil Liberties" (1958); and one issue of META, newsletter of the Metropolitan Educational Television Association (1959).
  - Clippings and ephemera, 1957, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
  - Member suggestions, 1957-1959, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
- Series VI. Financial, 1959-1987
  Contains assorted receipts, bank statements, and canceled checks. Loose material that was inserted in the account book in Folder 32 has been transferred to Folder 33. Some financial records are scattered throughout Series II, and abstracted treasurer's reports for the 1920s through 1949 may be found in Series III.
  - Account book, 1959-1987 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 32)
  - Loose items from account book, 1959-1987 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bank statements, 1964 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bank statements, 1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 35)